{"tossups": [{"question": "This man once walked all the way across Virginia lengthwise to secure a promised spot in college at Hampton. He promised to keep \"as separate as the five fingers on each hand\" and advocated that his followers \"cast down your bucket where you are.\" For 10 points, name this man whose Atlanta Compromise speech staked out a moderate civil rights position in 1895.", "answer": "Booker T. <b><u>Washington</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Early objects created using this device are called incunabula. This device was introduced to Venice by Aldus Manutius and brought to England by William Caxton. A goldsmith from Mainz used a screw-press for his \"movable-type\" version of this device. For 10 points, name this device first created in the West by Johannes Gutenberg.", "answer": "<b><u>printing press</u></b> [prompt on \"press\"]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Between political offices, this man was a law partner of future FCC commissioner Newton Minnow. This man snapped \"don't wait for the translation\" at Valerin Zorin during his time as U.S. ambassador to the United Nations. He was dubbed \"egghead\" during his two failed Presidential runs. For 10 points, name this man who lost twice to Dwight Eisenhower.", "answer": "Adlai <b><u>Stevenson</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was once marooned on Bermuda in the wreck of the <em>Sea Venture.</em> He created the Orinoco cultivar of a product that he put into four barels during his return to England, where he presented his wife, under the new name \"Rebecca,\" to the royal court. For 10 points, name this husband of Pocahontas who devised the financially viable form of American tobacco.", "answer": "John <b><u>Rolfe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1861, Johann Reis arguably accomplished this task by making use of magneto-restriction. Elisha Gray claimed to have accomplished this task, though he lost out on a patent to the man who is generally credited with this accomplishment and used the result to transmit, \"Watson, come here, I want you.\" For 10 points, name this achievement of Alexander Graham Bell.", "answer": "inventing the <b><u>telephone</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "President-in-waiting Luis Donaldo Colosio was assassinated in this city in 1994. This city's Avenida Revoluci\u00f3n (<b>ah-veh-NEE-duh reh-voh-loo-see-OWN</b>) was the location of Cesar Cardini's restaurant, where the Caesar salad was invented. For 10 points, name this city in Baja California which attracts numerous American tourists from nearby San Diego.", "answer": "<b><u>Tijuana</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This city constructed a paved road used to transport boats overland called the Diolkos. A dispute between this city and its colony of Corcyra was a cause of the Peloponnesian War. Cypselid rulers of this city included its second tyrant, Periander. Capitals bedecked with acanthus leaves characterized this city\u2019s namesake order of columns. For 10 points, name this ancient Greek city located on a namesake isthmus.", "answer": "<b><u>Corinth</u></b> [or <b><u>Korinthos</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A poem which became a protest song about this activity compares the \"scent of magnolias, sweet and fresh\" to the \"sudden smell of burning flesh.\" Federal attempts to crack down on this practice included the Dyer Bill. Ida B. Wells was an activist against this practice, which is the subject of \"Strange Fruit.\" For 10 points, identify this practice of extrajudicial mob killings of blacks.", "answer": "<b><u>lynching</u></b>s", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "One holder of this title boasted that his descendants would rule for 10,000 generations, though counting him they ruled for only two. That holder of this title followed Legalist precepts while burning subversive books and died after taking mercury pills in search of immortality. For 10 points, name this title taken by Qin Shi Huang and later used by leaders of the Han dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>emperor</u></b> of <b><u>China</u></b> [or <em>huang<b><u>di</u></b></em>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader forcibly dismissed the Rump Parliament and replaced it with Barebone\u2019s parliament. He was hated in Ireland for atrocities committed at Wexford and Drogheda. He helped win the Battle of Naseby as a cavalry commander in the New Model Army. For 10 points, name this man who served as Lord Protector of England in the interregnum following the execution of Charles I of England.", "answer": "Oliver <b><u>Cromwell</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 5 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was advised by the author of <em>Germany is Our Problem</em>, Henry Morgenthau, as well as by a man who later became a conservative, Raymond Moley. This man's unofficial advisors were recruited largely from Columbia University's law school and were led by Rexford Tugwell. The \"brain trust\" advised, for 10 points, what man during his four terms as U.S. President?", "answer": "<b><u>F</u></b>ranklin Delano <b><u>Roosevelt</u></b> [or <b><u>FDR</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Roosevelt</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire followed the proclamation of the Edict of Gulhane with a fifty year modernization effort called the Tanzimat Reforms. Some of its armies were composed of irregular \u201cbashi-bazouks,\u201d while others were composed of janissaries. It was known as the Sick Man of Europe leading up to World War I. For 10 points, name this empire which centered on Turkey.", "answer": "<b><u>Ottoman</u></b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A major genre innovation during this period was the concerto grosso (<b>con-CHAIR-toe GROSS-oh</b>), which was used extensively by Arcangelo Corelli. Another composer from this musical period wrote the <em>Goldberg Variations</em>. For 10 points, name this period in Western music history that included Johann Sebastian Bach, and came between the Renaissance and Classical eras.", "answer": "<b><u>Baroque</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This song asks \"where is that band who so vaultingly swore\" and observes \"where the foes' haughty host in dread silence reposes\" in its little-heard additional verses. The British bar song song \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" was used to set the lyrics of this song. For 10 points, name this song written during the British bombardment of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.", "answer": "\"The <b><u>Star-Spangled Banner</u></b>\"", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "A state park named for these people contains the Pioneer Monument and the Emigrant Trail Museum. This group of people suffered an early tragedy when John Snyder was murdered. This group's poor decision to attempt the Hastings Cutoff led to them being snowed in at Truckee Lake. For 10 points, name these people who resorted to cannibalism in the 1840s.", "answer": "<b><u>Donner</u></b> Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Martial law was declared in this nation after the First Quarter Storm. Cardinal Jaime Sin helped spearhead the overthrow of one leader of this nation. That leader\u2019s wife had a massive collection of shoes, which was left behind after the People\u2019s Power Revolution. For 10 points, name this Asian nation which was formerly ruled by Ferdinand Marcos.", "answer": "the <b><u>Philippines</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This procedure occurred to the writer of <em>Forever Amber</em> and <em>Laura</em>. This process required the author of <em>Johnny Get You Gun</em> to adopt the alias \"Robert Rich.\" For 10 points, name this process which was performed on Ring Lardner, Jr., Dalton Trumbo, and others in the Hollywood Ten, who were denied work in the film industry due to their membership in the Communist Party.", "answer": "<b><u>blacklist</u></b>ing", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In mid-2014, popular examples of this kind of product included the Moto 360 and Pebble</u></b> <b><u>Steel. Samsung launched several of these products under the (+)</u> \"Gear\" line, and these products are named for a Sony line that integrates with (*)</b> Android operating systems. For 10 points, Apple caused a stir by announcing the launch of their version of what kind of wearable technology product, which is often used for fitness monitoring or portable media capabilities?", "answer": "<b><u>smart watch</u></b>es", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man\u2019s father was an Olympic boxer for Iran, while he himself won the 1996</u></b> <b><u>Olympic gold medal in men\u2019s singles for tennis. In the early 1990\u2019s, he attracted</u></b> <b><u>controversy for his flamboyant (+)</u> dress, but also gained an endorsement deal for Canon</b> <b>cameras where he said the tagline, \u201cImage is everything.\u201d He is the most recent American</b> <b>to achieve the career (*)</b> Grand Slam, and he is married to German legend Steffi Graf. For 10 points, name this tennis player and Las Vegas native, who was perhaps the greatest rival to Pete Sampras.", "answer": "Andre <b><u>Agassi</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>In Norse mythology, it was believed that the world-ending Ragnarok would include the</u></b> <b><u>wolf Skoll finally succeeding in his quest to eat this object. The national god of the Incas,</u></b> <b><u>Inti, was the god of this thing. Japanese (+)</u> emperors once titled themselves as descendants of a goddess of this thing, (*)</b> Amaterasu. Similarly, Egyptians placed great importance on the main god of this thing, Ra. For 10 points, name this astronomical body often worshipped by polytheists.", "answer": "the <b><u>sun</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was embarrassed by the 2002 release of Nixon White House tapes in which he</u></b> <b><u>accused Jews of belonging to the \"synagogue of Satan.\" This man, who has taken credit for</u></b> <b><u>convincing Dwight Eisenhower to (+)</u> desegregate schools in Arkansas, became famous for his Festival of Hope and (*)</b> ecumenical revivals, which close with the hymn \"Just As I Am.\" For 10 points, name this frequent Presidential advisor and most successful evangelist in American history.", "answer": "Billy <b><u>Graham</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this film, the title character builds a Chicago opera house in an attempt to make his</u></b> <b><u>second wife, Susan Alexander, into a movie star. Jerry Thompson attempts to research the</u></b> <b><u>life of this film\u2019s title character, who had built the (+)</u> Xanadu estate. This movie begins</b> <b>with its title character dropping a snowglobe after whispering the word (*)</b> \u201cRosebud.\u201d For 10 points, name this Orson Welles movie about a newspaper magnate.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Citizen Kane</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man replaced Vin Diesel in the lead role for the sequel</u> </b><em><b><u>XxX: State of the Union</u></b></em><b><u>. This</u></b> <b><u>man was attacked by his former bandmates on the EP</u> </b><em><b><u>100 Miles and Runnin</u></b></em><b><u> at the same</u></b> <b><u>time that he released his solo debut, (+)</u></b> <em><b>AmeriKKKa's Most Wanted</b></em><b>. This star of the (*) </b><em>Barbershop</em> series wrote more lyrics for NWA than any other member. For 10 points, name this gangsta rapper turned family comedian, the star of the <em>Are We There Yet?</em> movies.", "answer": "<b><u>Ice Cube</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man commissioned a battle flag with a motto sewn on it that he attributed to James</u></b> <b><u>Lawrence, \"Don't Give Up the Ship.\" This man opposed Jesse Elliot, the captain of the</u></b> <em><b><u>Niagara</u></b></em><b><u>, at (+)</u> Put-In Bay. He issued the message \"We have (*)</b> met the enemy and they are ours\" to his commander in the field, William Henry Harrison. For 10 points, name this naval commander who defeated the British at the Battle of Lake Erie during the War of 1812.", "answer": "Oliver Hazard <b><u>Perry</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's central bank adopted a policy of \u201cforward guidance\u201d for future interest</u></b> <b><u>rates after the 2008 financial crisis. It froze Icelandic bank assets in 2008 after Iceland</u></b> <b><u>refused to guarantee its banks' debts to creditors in this country. The Chancellor of the (+)</u></b> <b>Exchequer proposed large spending cuts in 2010 as part of the austerity program of its</b> <b>current prime minister, (*)</b> David Cameron. For 10 points, name this country whose government nationalized the Royal Bank of Scotland.", "answer": "<b><u>United Kingdom</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 5 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>Charles Ogle mockingly accused Martin van Buren of eating with a spoon made of these</u></b> <b><u>substance. A speech about this substance exclaimed \"you shall not press down upon the</u></b> <b><u>brow of labor this (+)</u> crown of thorns.\" This substance was sought by men who went to the (*)</b> Klondike, the 49ers, and other prospectors. For 10 points, name this substance whose \"standard\" was, until 1971, the basis of American money.  ANSWER: <b><u>gold</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}